Guide to the Richard Charles Lee Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Richard Charles Lee papers
1934-2000
MS 318
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
148.24
(258 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, memoranda, position papers, reports, speeches, appointment books, photographs, scrapbooks, and films documenting the career of Richard C. Lee, mayor of New Haven, 1954-1969. The Lee Papers document the professional and public life of Lee, not his personal life. The papers contain correspondence and other materials on the practice of urban politics, urban renewal, New Haven's efforts in the war on poverty, civil rights and race relations, town-gown relations, and his interaction with local and state Democratic Party leaders. The papers also include campaign files covering the period 1949-1968, appointment books, photographs documenting the course of redevelopment, a small amount of material on Lee's life after he left office, and political scrapbooks.
Lee, Richard C. (Richard Charles), 1916-2003
Conditions Governing Access
Researchers must sign "Access agreement for the Richard C. Lee Papers."
Box 151 is closed until 2045.
Accessions 2001-M-010 and 2001-M-017 are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Existence and Location of Copies
Scrapbooks, Series VII, on microfilm HM150 (10,195 frames on 10 reels, 35mm.) reproduced by Yale University Library, 1983.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Richard C. Lee, 1983-1990, 2000; gift of Noel A. Cazenave, 1993; and gift of Mrs. Charles Parker, 2011.
Arrangement
Arranged in seven series and seventeen additions: I. Mayoral Files, 1943-1969. II. Subject Files, 1934-1969. III. Campaign Files, 1945-1973. IV. Appointment Books, 1944-1976. V. Photographs, 1947-1969. VI. Post-Mayoral Files, 1970-1983. VII. Scrapbooks, 1947-1968.
Scope and Contents
The Richard C. Lee Papers document the public years of one of the best known mayors in the United States. The bulk of the papers cover the period 1954-1969, when Lee was mayor of New Haven, although the papers span the dates 1934-1983. The Lee Papers were donated to Yale University by Mayor Lee in 1983 and are restricted until 1996. For related material, see the Edward Joseph Logue Papers (MS 959).
The papers are divided into seven series. The largest and most important series, MAYORAL FILES, comes first. It fills 106 boxes and consists of general administrative office files, arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically by subject, kept during Lee's eight terms as New Haven mayor. Series I contains an extensive amount of material documenting Lee's skills as an urban politician in a city dominated by ethnic groups. MAYORAL FILES also have information on his public relations activities, his relationship with his constituents, his leadership in urban renewal, New Haven's pioneer efforts in the war on poverty, his civil rights record, town-gown relations, and his interaction with prominent local and state Democratic politicians.
Mayor Richard C. Lee was a superb urban politician who was skilled in the nuts and bolts practices of ethnic politics. Material on this subject permeates the Lee Papers and researchers who examine the collection carefully will find massive evidence to support the view that the mayor was a master urban politician who excelled in the practices of local ethnic politics, was always aware of the necessity of favorable publicity, and was acutely sensitive to constituent needs and desires. For information on Lee's ethnic political concerns, see, by way of example, his 1958 journey to Ireland, Italy, and Israel, Boxes 19-20, folders 466-474; the files for George W. Crawford and John M. Golden; and Series IV, APPOINTMENT BOOKS, Boxes 131-39, which show the importance Lee attached to attending wakes. Since few of Lee's major policy initiatives were favorably received by the conservative Republican Jackson newspapers, the Register and Journal-Courier, the mayor was concerned with generating the maximum favorable publicity for himself and his administration. For examples of this concern, see Box 16, folder 406; Box 37, folder 796, and Box 39, folder 840. The mayor particularly stressed good constituent relations. He was genuinely interested in aiding constituents facing difficulties with government and they in turn seemed to view him as an ombudsman, someone to turn to as a last resort for help in solving problems and in coping with the city bureaucracy. The papers contains hundreds of letters from ordinary citizens asking for assistance in obtaining better housing, expressing concern about traffic safety, asking for welfare assistance, offering advice, and thanking him for his aid in resolving problems. See, for example, Box 24, folder 531; Box 25, folder 533; Box 43, folders 893 and 895; and Box 47, folder 973.
The Lee Papers also contain ample material that delineate the mayor's personal and political relationships with such important New Haven and Connecticut politicians as John M. Bailey, Arthur T. Barbieri, William Benton, Chester Bowles, John N. Dempsey, Thomas J. Dodd, Robert N. Giaimo, John M. Golden, Edward L. Marcus, and Abraham A. Ribicoff, but little to document the close relationship between Lee and President John F. Kennedy. See the files for these men in Series I and Series II. Likewise, although one can find a good deal of information in correspondence in 1957-1958, 1962, and 1969-1970 concerning Lee's ambition to seek a U.S. Senate seat, a convincing explanation for the mayor's failure to seek higher office is not given.
The major substantive thrust of Lee's administrations was in the area of urban renewal. The mayor's leadership in this area won him a well-deserved national reputation as a progressive and spokesman for redevelopment. Those interested in studying this critically important aspect of Lee's incumbency should examine several different files in Series I, the most important being Citizens Action Commission; City Plan; Connecticut, State of: Highway Department; Housing; Redevelopment; and Traffic and Parking, Department of.
Many well known city planners played significant roles in the redevelopment process. Among the best known are Maurice Rotival, an internationally known urban planner; H. Gordon Sweet, Executive Director of the Citizens Action Commission from 1954 to 1959 and later Assistant Director of the New Haven Redevelopment Agency; Edward J. Logue, Development Administrator 1955-1961; H. Ralph Taylor, Executive Director, New Haven Redevelopment Agency 1955-1959; L. Thomas Appleby, Executive Director, New Haven Redevelopment Agency 1959-1961 and Development Administrator 1961-1965; Melvin J. Adams, Executive Director of the Redevelopment Agency from December 1962 to February 1965 and Development Administrator 1965-1969; Norris C. Andrews, City Planning Director 1954-1962; and Robert T. Wolfe, Executive Director of the Housing Authority of the City of New Haven. Material on these men and their careers in New Haven can be found under the agencies in which they served; the subjects of Citizens Action Commission, City Plan, and Redevelopment; and under their names.
New Haven's city planners focused on efforts to revive the commercial base of a decaying central city and to upgrade the quality of city housing. The difficulties caused by the condemnation and destruction of older buildings for both businesses and poor families are detailed. The files for Housing are particularly useful for the information they contain on the relocation problems of the poor, elderly, and disabled.
A whole series of major redevelopment projects was undertaken, beginning with the construction of the Oak Street Connector, then with the Church Street, Wooster Square, Long Wharf, and University Towers projects, followed by still others. Mayor Lee was interested, however, not only in the physical reconstruction of the city, but also with the architectural quality of the buildings being erected. Many well known architects designed structures that were at least in part intended to make New Haven an architectural showpiece in America. See the Redevelopment files. The centerpiece for redevelopment was intended to be a new government center whose construction would require the removal of the library, court house, city hall, and post office, an undertaking that would transform the character of the entire region around the New Haven Green. Preservationists rallied in opposition to this plan in 1966 and the development was never built, primarily because the General Services Administration failed to endorse the plans of architect I.M. Pei and chose, according to Lee, an undistinguished local firm that specialized in political contacts. Please see Box 83, folder 1514; Box 84, folder 1520; and Box 85, folder 1542.
New Haven was also in the forefront of the war on poverty. In 1962 Community Progress, Inc., established with a $2,500,000 grant from the Ford Foundation, became one of the first anti-poverty agencies formed in the United States. Its purpose was to improve educational, employment, recreational, and housing opportunities for residents of the declining areas of the city. Headed by Mitchell Sviridoff, CPI began to attack the problems of unemployment and poor inner city education with job training and "head start" programs. See the files for Community Progress, Inc. and Ford Foundation for information on this important subject.
Mayor Lee was also concerned with civil rights and race relations. As soon, as he took office in 1954, he ordered the destruction of all personnel forms asking the question whether a person was "white or colored." (Box 2, folder 35). He also appointed George W. Crawford as corporation counsel, the first black to ever hold a high appointed or elected office in New Haven. For additional information on civil rights and race relations in New Haven, see the files fo NAACP 1954-64; Human Relations Council 1955-1962, 1969; Human Relations Advisor 1957-1962; CORE 1962; and Human Relations Committee 1963. In Series II, SUBJECT FILES, see also NAACP, Negro Participation, and Sit-Outs. It was widely believed that New Haven, because of its reputation as a model city, would be immune from the racial tensions and street violence that spread through American cities during the late 1960's. The shock, therefore, was all the greater when racial violence broke out in August 1967. On these events, see the files for Curfew proclamations 1967; Disturbance 1967; Police; Urban Violence 1968 and 1969; and Series II Riots, racial matters.
Another important subject treated in the Lee Papers is that of town-gown relations. The Yale University files and many subject files contain information in the close, and generally warm, relationship between Lee and Yale. Because of his years at the Yale News Bureau and his friendship with President A. Whitney Griswold, Lee was able to tap the considerable resources of the University in support of urban renewal, charter reform, and civil rights. Among those who served New Haven in official and unofficial capacities in addition to Griswold were Eugene V. Rostow, Ira V. Hiscock, Myres S. McDougal, C.-E.A. Winslow, Louis H. Pollack, Reuben A. Holden, and Sidney Lovett.
Those interested in many other aspects of New Haven life between 1954 and 1968 can find a great deal of useful information through examination of the appropriate files over a period of years. Those wishing to study the New Haven airport, education, the highway program, the importance of parks and recreation, patronage and welfare problems can follow these subjects in Series I of the Richard C. Lee Papers.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Charles Lee was born in New Haven on March 12, 1916. After graduating from high school in 1934, he became a city hall reporter for the New Haven Journal-Courier where he developed his interest in politics. In 1939 he was elected to the city board of aldermen and began working for the New Haven Chamber of Commerce as associate secretary. Following an honorable discharge after a brief stint in the U.S. Army, he resumed his aldermanic position in 1943 and began working for Yale University, first with the wartime publication, Yale News Digest, and then as director of the News Bureau. In 1949 and 1951 he ran unsuccessfully for mayor of New Haven, but on his third attempt in 1953, he was elected. He served for eight terms from 1954 to 1969. His administration was noted for its leadership in urban renewal and success in obtaining federal money to carry out the redevelopment projects. He also served as president of the United States Conference of Mayors from 1962 to 1963. Lee died on February 2, 2003.
Airports -- Connecticut -- New Haven; City planning -- Connecticut -- New Haven; City planning -- Connecticut; Economic assistance, Domestic -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Elections -- Connecticut; Mayors -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- Elections; Mayors -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Playgrounds -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Public opinion -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Schools -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Urban renewal -- Connecticut -- New Haven; New Haven (Conn.) -- Officials and employees; New Haven (Conn.) -- Politics and government; New Haven (Conn.) -- Race relations; United States -- Politics and government; Photographs; Mayors; Politicians; Adams, Melvin J.; Andrews, Norris C.; Appleby, L. Thomas; Bailey, John M. (John Moran), 1904-1975; Barbieri, Arthur T.; Benton, William, 1900-1973; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986; Crawford, George W. (George Williamson), 1877-; Dempsey, John N.; Dodd, Thomas J. (Thomas Joseph), 1907-1971; Giaimo, Robert N.; Golden, John M.; Griswold, Alfred Whitney, 1906-1963; Lee, Richard C. (Richard Charles), 1916-2003; Logue, Edward J.; Marcus, Edward L., 1927-; Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910-1998; Rotival, Maurice Emile Henri; Sviridoff, Mitchell, 1918-; Sweet, H. Gordon; Taylor, H. Ralph (Harold Ralph), 1918-; Wolfe, Robert T.; Community Progress, Inc; Yale University -- Public relations
- Mayoral Files, 1943-1969; Series I; 44 linear feet (106 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, MAYORAL FILES, contains correspondence, memos, memoranda, position papers, and other similar materials covering the years 1954-69, when Richard C. Lee was mayor of New Haven. Three folders in Box 1 have material for the period 1943-53.
  All files are arranged chronologically and alphabetically in accordance with their arrangement in Mayor Lee's office. There are files for subjects, like Citizen Action Commission, and for people, like Maurice Rotival. Most files cover a single year or portion thereof and are found in one alphabetical listing per year. It is necessary therefore, for researchers wishing to follow a subject over a period of years to examine the box and folder listing for each year. Material is arranged in chronological order within each folder.
  The mayor's office also established "Letter" general files, i.e. "L" general and "R" general. In these files correspondence is arranged alphabetically by surname of person or subject and then chronologically. Researchers should make certain to examine the "Letter" general files on people and subjects that may be unlisted or unlisted for a particular year
  - Miscellaneous, 1943-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Redevelopment, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1954
    - Airport (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Aldermen, Board of (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Federation of State, County, Municipal Employees (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Municipal Association (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Appointments (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Assessors, Board of (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Association for Retarded Children in Greater New Haven, Inc. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "B" general (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Braverman, R. R. & Co. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bridges (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Budget (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Budget hearing (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Building Department (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bush, Prescott (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "C" general (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Cabinet (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Capital Budget Program (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Charter (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Charter Revision Commission (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Charter Revision Commission: minutes (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Charter Revision Commission: minutes (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Citizens Action Commission; general (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - Citizens Action Commission: industrial and harbor development (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Citizens Action Commission: Industrial and Harbor Development Committee (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Citizens Action Commision: Sweet, H. Gorden (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Citizens Advisory Committee on Education (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - City Engineer (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - City Plan (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Connecticut Development Commission (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Connecticut, State of: Highway Department (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Controller (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "D" general (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Dixwell Community House (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - East Shore Parkway (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Education, Department of (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Education, Department of: school visits (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Environmental Sanitation, Bureau of (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "F" general (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Fluoridation (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Gregson Street (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - "H" general (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Harbor development (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Housing Authority (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Housing Code (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Industrial Advisory Council for the City of New Haven (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "J" general (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Juvenile Delinquency, Commission on (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "K" general (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Knights of Columbus (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - "L" general (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Lodge, Governor John (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "M" general (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Mayor's Commission on Administrative Economy (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "N" general (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - N. A. A. C. P. (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - New Haven Colony Historical Society (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - New Haven Foundation (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - "O" general (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Oak Street Connector (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - "P" general (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Park Department (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Public Works (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - "R" general (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Redevelopment Agency (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Rotival, Maurice (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Schuckman, Fred A. (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Southern New England Telephone Company (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - "T" general (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Traffic (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Veterans Information (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Welfare, Department of (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Welfare, Department of: Springside Home (Box 3, Folder 77-78)
    - "XYZ" general (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - 1955
    - Airport (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Aldermen, Board of (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Aldermen, Board of: resolutions (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - American Municipal Association (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Animal Shelter (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Assessors, Board of (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - "B" general (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Braverman, Rubin R. (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Budget (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Building Department (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - "C" general (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Cabinet (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Capital Budget (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Chamber of Commerce: New Haven (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Children's Building Commission (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Citizens Action Commission: Central Business District (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Citizens Action Commission: education (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Citizens Action Commission: general (Box 4, Folder 97-98)
    - Citizens Action Commission: health and welfare (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Citizens Action Commission: housing (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Citizens Action Commission: human relations (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Citizens Action Commission: industrial and harbor development (Box 4, Folder 102-103)
    - Citizens Action Commission: luncheon (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Citizens Action Commission: market (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Citizens Action Commission: Metropolitan Approach Committee (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Citizens Action Commission: minutes (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Citizens Action Commision: Sweet, H. Gordon (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - City Engineer (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - City Hall Project (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - City Plan (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - City Plan Commission: annual report (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Clark, Joseph S. (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Connecticut Company (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Connecticut, State of: Highway Department (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Controller, Office of (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Corporation Counsel (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - "D" general (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - "Dying City" (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - "E" general (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Education, Department of (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Education, Department of: high schools (Box 5, Folder 122-123)
    - Education, Department of: school visits (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Environmental Sanitation, Bureau of (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Finance, Board of (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Flood Disaster (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - Fluoridation (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - "G" general (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - Garage, supply house and warehouse (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - Golden, John M. (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - Gregson Street (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - "H" general (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Housing Authority (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - Human Relations Council (Box 6, Folder 136)
    - Humane Commission (Box 6, Folder 137)
    - Hurricane (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Insurance (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - Invitations (Box 6, Folder 140)
    - Isbrandtsen Lines (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - "J" general (Box 6, Folder 142)
    - Juvenile delinquency (Box 6, Folder 143)
    - "K" general (Box 6, Folder 144)
    - Knights of Columbus (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - "L" general (Box 6, Folder 146)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - Legislation (Box 6, Folder 148)
    - Library (Box 6, Folder 149)
    - "M" general (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - Mayor's Commission on Juvenile Delinquency (Box 6, Folder 151)
    - "N" general (Box 6, Folder 152)
    - N. A. A. C. P. (Box 6, Folder 153)
    - New Haven Teacher's League (Box 6, Folder 154)
    - New York, New Haven, & Hartford Railroad Company (Box 6, Folder 155)
    - "O" general (Box 6, Folder 156)
    - Oak Street Connector (Box 6, Folder 157)
    - "P" general (Box 6, Folder 158)
    - P. T. A. (Box 7, Folder 159)
    - Park Department (Box 7, Folder 160)
    - Parking Authority (Box 7, Folder 161)
    - Philadelphia trip (Box 7, Folder 162)
    - Public Works Department (Box 7, Folder 163)
    - Purchasing Department (Box 7, Folder 164)
    - "R" general (Box 7, Folder 165)
    - Redevelopment Agency (Box 7, Folder 166)
    - Rotival, Maurice (Box 7, Folder 167)
    - "S" general (Box 7, Folder 168)
    - Southern New England Telephone Company (Box 7, Folder 169)
    - Springside Home (Box 7, Folder 170)
    - "T" general (Box 7, Folder 171)
    - Traffic (Box 7, Folder 172)